[MUSIC]
[음악]
So, we now built a whole new kind of restaurant experience, or
분류기로 아주 새로운 레스토랑 리뷰 경험을
restaurant review experience, using classifiers.
제공했습니다
Let's dig in and really understand a little bit more what a classifier is,
깊이 들어가서 분류기가 뭔지와
and some other applications of classification.
분류의 다른 응용 분야에 대해서 알아봅시다
So a classifier takes some input x, for example a sentence from the review or
분류기는 입력 x를 받는데 예를 들어
other inputs as we'll see.
리뷰 등의 문장입니다
It pushes it through what's called a model to output some value y,
모델에 입력을 밀어넣어 y를 출력하게 하는데
that we're trying to predict.
우리가 예측하고자 하는 결과값이죠
And here it's a class, for example, positive or negative.
여기선 클래스죠 긍정적인지 부정적인지
So positive in the case of sentiment analysis corresponds with thumbs up
감성 분석에서 긍정적이면
reviews, while negative corresponds with thumbs down.
강추가 되겠고 부정적이면 비추가 되겠죠
But this is just one example of classification.
이는 분류의 한 예에 불과합니다
You can look at text, for example, a web page, I want
텍스트를 보고, 웹페이지라고 하죠,
to figure out which webpages interest me, and I can align them to categories.
어떤 웹페이지가 관심사에 속하는지 카테고리별로 정리하고 싶습니다
For example, is this about education, a page about education,
주제가 교육인지
is it a page about finance, is it a page about technology and so on?
금융인지 기술인지 등입니다
So, there's not just two categories.
두 카테고리만 있는 게 아니죠
There can be three, four, or
셋, 넷, 다섯, 심지어 천 개의
even thousands of categories I'm predicting from.
카테고리에서 예측해야 할지도 모릅니다
Now, another example of classification,
분류의 또 다른 예는
which really has impacted all of our lives, is in spam filtering.
우리의 삶에 지대한 영향을 끼친 것인데 스팸 필터링입니다
Some of you might remember, perhaps in the early 2000s, what spam filters were like.
몇몇 분들은 2000년대 초반에 스팸 필터가 어땠는지 기억하실지도 모르겠네요
The quality was not very good.
성능이 좋지 않았죠
Really, they were all hand-tuned things where somebody said,
직접 사람 손으로 조정해서
oh it has certain words, it must be spam.
이런 말을 했으면 스팸일거라고 걸러냈습니다
But the spammers kept changing the words a little bit,
하지만 스패머들은 단어를 계속해서 조금씩 바꾸고
adding numbers instead of letters, and beating the spam filters.
글자 대신에 숫자를 넣거나 해서 스팸 필터를 무력화시켰습니다
And what really changed the world of spam filtering.
지금의 스팸 필터링은 그때와는 완전히 다르지요
It changed it so much that I don't even look at my spam folder, actually, sorry if
얼마나 좋아졌는지 이젠 스팸 폴더에 들어가보지도 않습니다
your message went to my spam folder, I just don't open it, is machine learning.
스팸 폴더에 들어갔다면 안 열어봅니다 기계학습 알고리즘이 알아서 했을 테니까요
It's classifiers.
분류기가요
They took the input x of the email and
이메일 입력 x를 받아다 분류기에 집어넣으면
they fed it through a classifier that predicted whether it's spam or not.
스팸인지 아닌지 예측합니다
It did that really well.
상당히 정확하죠
And it does it by not just looking at the text of the email, but
이메일의 텍스트만 아니라
it looks at other characteristics.
다른 특성도 살펴봅니다
So for example, who sent it.
예를 들어 누가 보냈는지
If it somebody's whose a close friend, or somebody you have lots of vacation,
가까운 친구나 같이 휴가 가는 사이라면
with it's less likely to be spam.
스팸이 아닐 확률이 높겠죠
The IP address is a person sending from the usual computer and so on.
평소 자주 보내는 사람 컴퓨터의 IP 주소인지도 봅니다
Lots of information.
많은 정보가 있죠
So this is another really interesting practical application.
아주 흥미로운 실용적 응용이죠
In computer vision, we do a lot of classification.
컴퓨터 비전에도 분류 작업이 많습니다
We'll take an image, and figure out what is in that image.
이미지를 가져다 그 안 내용물을 알아냅니다
For example, here, the input x are the pixels of the image.
예를 들어 입력 x는 이미지 픽셀입니다
We feed it to a classifier, and
분류기에 집어넣어
we're going to predict things like is this a dog?
개인지 예측합니다
In fact it's a Labrador Retriever, Golden Retriever, or a different kind of dog.
개라도 래브라도 리트리버, 골든 리트리버, 아니면 다른 종류일 수도 있습니다
This is actually my dog, Labrador Retriever.
이건 래브라도 리트리버인 제 개입니다
And as we will see later on in the deep learning module,
나중에 딥러닝 모듈에서 보게 될텐데
there's really interesting new ways of doing this with very high accuracy.
아주 높은 정확도를 가진 방법이 새로 나왔습니다
Now you can also use classification in medical diagnosis systems, and
의사가 하는 의료진단 시스템에도
in fact this is what your doctor does.
활용할 수 있습니다
They take your temperature, maybe they look at your x-ray, they look at some
온도, x-ray, 임상 검사 등을 통해
medical tests and they try to make a prediction about what's ailing somebody.
병의 원인을 예측합니다
Maybe they say nah, nah, you're just healthy, or you have a cold,
별 게 아니라 건강할 수도 있지만 감기,
you have the flu, maybe even you have pneumonia.
독감, 심지어 폐렴일지도 모릅니다
That's a variable y that's being predicted,
변수 y이 진행 중인
what is the disease that's going on.
병에 대한 예측입니다
Now these days, there's really interesting new things around personalized medicine,
최근 들어 맞춤약을 둘러싸고 여러 흥미로운 연구들이
because the prediction doesn't just depend on the standard measurements, but
진행되고 있는데 예측이 표준적인 측정에만 의지하지
can be really personalized for me.
않고 나라는 개인에게 맞춰서 나오기 때문입니다
Can depend on my particular DNA sequencing, which is pretty exciting and
특정 DNA 염기 서열이나
also my lifestyle, which maybe look something like
왼쪽 밑 그림 같은 생활 습관이나
or maybe more realistic, something like this.
좀 더 현실적으론 이런 게 있을 수 있죠
And so, given all these measurements,
이런 측정치를 통해
can make an even better prediction at what's ailing me.
병의 원인에 대해 더 정확한 예측을 할 수 있습니다
Now this idea of classification in off-machine learning,
기계학습에서 분류란 개념은
has really gone much further, even to be able to read your mind.
더욱 발전해서 마음까지 읽어낼 정도가 되었습니다
So when I was at Carnegie-Mellon, Tom Mitchell, one of my friends and colleagues
카네기 멜론에 있을 때 제 친구이자 옆 사무실 동료인
at his office next door, and he come to me and says, we've done this amazing thing.
톰 밋첼이 어느 날 저에게 와서 대단한 걸 했다고 말했습니다
Which would take an image of your brain using a technology called FMRI,
FMRI이란 기술로 뇌 영상을 찍는
which is brain scan, and predict when you're reading a word of text,
뇌 촬영을 통해 특정 텍스트를 읽으면
whether you're reading the word hammer or the word house.
망치를 읽었는지 집을 읽었는지 알아낸다고 합니다
So it's really reading your mind.
정말로 마음을 읽는 거죠
But in fact, he went on to do many interesting things.
그 외에 흥미로운 작업을 많이 했습니다
For example, if you're looking at a picture of a hammer or a house, but
예를 들어 망치나 집의 그림을 보았을 때
you train the classified on them you reading words hammers and house,
분류기는 망치와 집이란 단어만 가지고 훈련시켰는데도
you're still able to read your mind and figure out what picture you're looking at.
마음을 읽어서 어떤 그림을 보는지 알아냅니다
So this is yet
앞으로 뇌를 이해하기 위한
the next frontier of classification to understand how the brain works.
분류의 차기 첨단분야가 될 겁니다
[MUSIC]
[음악]